<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvver to a late pamphlet; entituled, A character of a Popish successor, and what England may expect from such a one</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75406</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3308</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231776</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897609</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897609</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137224</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75406)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137224)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2505:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvver to a late pamphlet; entituled, A character of a Popish successor, and what England may expect from such a one</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, 8-15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>re-printed,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Dom. 1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Settle, Elkanah.  The character of a popish successour.</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Settle, Elkanah, 1648-1724. --  Character of a popish successour --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137224:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER To a late Pamphlet; Entituled, A CHARACTER OF A Popiſh Succeſſor, AND WHAT ENGLAND May expect from ſuch a One.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Virtus repulſae neſcia ſordidae,</l>
                  <l>Incontaminatis fulget Honoribus.</l>
                  <l>Nec ponit aut ſumit ſecures,</l>
                  <l>Arbitrio Popularis aurae;</l>
                  <l>Virtus negata tentat Iter via. <bibl>Hor.</bibl>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Re-printed, <hi>Anno</hi> DOM. 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:137224:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:137224:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE CHARACTER OF A Popish Succeſſor.</head>
            <p>HAving Intended to make ſome ſlight Reply, (ſuch as my own weakneſs could produce, and my Adverſaries did require) to a late Pamphlet, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Character of a Popiſh Succeſſor:</hi> I thought I was bound to do him ſo much Juſtice as to let our Reader know, that however incoherent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictorie his Diſcourſe or his Reaſonings are, yet his Principles are not ſo; but that they are quite through the ſame, and maintain a moſt exact and cloſe agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween themſelves. This wil appear by conſidering how truly the parts of his whole Book corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond to one another, to repreſent (as in a Picture) the late Rebellion, to which it bears the exacteſt Reſemblance; For like that it begins, (in the very firſt Page) with <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> of <hi>Religion, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property;</hi> and like that too it continues, p. 16. to <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure and Revile the Emperial Root, and not only to ſtiffen the knees that would bow to a Crown'd Head,</hi> but alſo to arm againſt it, the hands that ſhould defend it, by exhorting the people (p. 34.) <hi>not to be ſubdu'd like leſs then</hi> Engliſh-<hi>men, but to Reſiſt and Repel a King under the Name of an Invader.</hi> And like that too would it end, if theſe men who appear ſo <hi>Jealous</hi> and ſo <hi>Fearful</hi> could either prevail upon the Credulity of the Vulgar ſo far as to make their Jealouſies appear Juſt, or could themſelves bring to paſſe all their own <hi>Fears,</hi> that ſo they might be indeed (as our Author ſuppoſes them) <hi>Prophetick.</hi> For truly in this ſenſe they are likeſt to be ſo, and our State Prophets will appear like <hi>Nostradamus</hi> his Son, (a pretender to his Fathers Art) of whom the Story goes, that he was caught one night a Firing that City which He himſelf had Propheſied ſhould be burnt. And yet theſe are the <hi>Wiſe,</hi> and theſe <hi>are the Great,</hi> whom our Author would have us <hi>take delight to behold the reſtleſſe and uneaſie rolling about our troubled Sea-like Porpoiſes to forwarn us of a Tempeſt.</hi> But is not our Author miſtaken in his <hi>Simile?</hi> Alas, theſe are not the forewarning Porpoiſes, but the Leviathans themſelves, that ſport and take their paſtime in our troubled deep, whoſe reſtleſs and uneaſie rolling does not foretel, but is it ſelf the Storm. A Storm which once more is ready to ſhatter this Royal Veſſel (the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Kingdom) into pieces; <hi>O navis referent in mare Te novi fluctus.</hi> Theſe O <hi>England,</hi> are the ſame diſturbers of thy Calm Waters, which the ſecond time are like to raiſe the Waves ſo high, as to break all thy Anchors, looſen all thy Cables, and force thee out again into that Red Sea of Blood in which ſo lately thou haſt ſuffer'd Shipwrack; unleſſe in the cauſe of its Image here on Earth, the Majeſty of Heaven it ſelf haſts to our aſſiſtance; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137224:3"/>He, (as himſelf ſpeaks to his Servant <hi>Job,</hi>) <hi>Put a book into the Jaws of theſe Leviathans, and draw them out;</hi> unleſſe He exert thoſe Two mighty effects of his Divine Power, which the Pſalmiſt joyns together as the higheſt proofs of his Omnipotence, <hi>viz.</hi> Unleſſe <hi>he ſtills the rage of the Sea, and the madneſs of the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And amidſt this our evident danger, I muſt needs confeſſe with our Pamphleteer, that I cannot chuſe but account thoſe perſons very little our Friends, nay indeed void of Humanity it ſelf, that would lull us aſleep in the ſight of approaching ruine and deſtruction. But on the other hand, I can by no ways approve of thoſe for our Phyſicians, who uſe ſuch violent means to wake us out of our Security, as if there were no Cure for a Lethargy, but caſting us into a Raving Frenzie. And indeed ſuch has been the Phyſick of our State Mountebanks; and ſince they have poſſeſt the People with ſo deſperate a madneſſe, and raiſ'd ſuch diſmal apprehenſions in the minds of the undiſcerning multitude; I thought it the duty both of a Chriſtian and an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, to uſe the moſt effectual means of reſtoring us once more to our Wits again, and to reſcue, (if poſſible,) the Nation, out of that moſt miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which <hi>David</hi> has reckon'd among the grievouſeſt Plagues of the wicked; of whom he ſays, <hi>They were afraid, where no fear was:</hi> In order to which, I ſhal rally againſt thoſe Arguments which ſome have raiſed to ſave us, and which our Author has to his power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed to deſtroy us.</p>
            <p>P. 2. As firſt they ſay, <hi>Why ſhould we ſtand in fear of Popery, when in the preſent Temper of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, <hi>'tis impoſſible for any Succeſſor to introduce it?</hi> Ay why indeed? The Gentleman is at a ſtand, and is loath to venture his Serpents Teeth againſt the File; ſo leaves this Argument, and away to the next. Though I can't ſee why the ſame man, who preſently after has the courage to undertake the proving, that the four Cardinal Vertues are more dangerous in a Prince than their four oppoſite Vices, ſhould here want the ſame fool-hardineſſe to juſtifie the fears even of impoſſible things.</p>
            <p>The next Argument (which he undertakes to overthrow, and which yet ſtands firm and unſhaken by all his empty batteries and airy aſſaults,) is drawn from the conſideration of the Perſonal Excellencies inherent in that Prince, whom God and Nature, and the Laws of the Land hath pointed out to Us, as the unqueſtionable Lawful Succeſſor of the Crown and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of his Royal Brother. And if theſe are ſuch, and ſo many, as neither his Friends can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, or his Enemies deny; If the Royal Blood, (as often as his King or Countries Honor or Safety have call'd upon him,) has been as dangerouſly and as freely expoſed as that which fills the Veins of the vileſt Plebeian; If his Succeſs has been ſo equal to his Courage, that his Arms when (imploy'd abroad,) have ever been the love and wonder, and when at home (for ſuch to him was once the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Ocean) the Dread and Terrour of the neighbouring World; If his Friendſhips have ever been as firmly maintain'd, as they were judiciouſly choſen; If his Mouth and his Heart have always been ſo true to one another, that his Word has ever been as inviolate as the Oaths of others; And if this Noble Conſtancy of Truth has been in him the effect, as much of his Honour as his Conſcience; And if in a Lie he has ever thought as much to be deteſted as the Baſeneſſe of a Coward, as the Implety of a Villain; If his Juſtice has been acknowledged almoſt Divine, in this eſpecially, that it has never excluded all thoſe milder Vertues that might adorn a Crown, and make Majeſtie as amiable as it is Great: If all this be true, as none of his Adverſaries can deny, and ſome of his moſt inveterate Enemies have been forced even to confeſſe; I hope I ſhal be excuſed by my Readers, if I have ſo juſt a value for them, as to think that it would be an Affront in me to ſuſpect their Judgments, ſo much as to ſpend time in evincing to them how improbable a thing it would be, how contradictory to reaſon and common ſenſe, that the difference of a mans Opinion about ſome few diſputable matters of Faith, and not very material Ceremonies of Divine Worſhip, ſhould on a ſudden ruine and efface all thoſe good Characters of Magnanimity and Juſtice, of Generoſity and Goodneſſe, not ſlightly traced, but deeply ingraven in his breaſt, ſo early ingraven by Nature it ſelf, that like Letters cut in the tender Bark, they have not been worn out, but rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged by the growth of the Tree, nor are ever likely to diſappear, till the Trunk it ſelf that they adorn ſhal be no more. And yet if we will be pleaſed to believe our little Impertinent Rhetorician, all this and much more muſt neceſſarily follow; <hi>When Popery has got the Aſcendant, and</hi> Rome <hi>has once ſtamped him her Proſelyte. For what then ſignifie all the great paſt Actions of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:137224:3"/>a Princes Life? And how little an Impreſſion will all the recorded Glories leave behind them?</hi> (p. 2.) No track of 'em it ſeems is left, all his Virtues are fled; or which is worſe, if they ſtill remain, <hi>There is ſtone of 'em that ſhall not be a particular Inſtrument of our Deſtruction.</hi> Now in the name of all that is good, what does our Scribler mean; do Virtues themſelves turn Vices in a Roman Catholick? And do they become ſo really, even in contradiction of our ſenſes and experience that tells us to the contrary? This is ſuch a Miracle as would ſtagger even a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Faith: ſuch an abſurdity as would make a Prieſt Bluſh; and which equals, if not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes, even Tranſubſtantiation it ſelf; the Scripture therefore has a peculiar denunciation of Judgment againſt the Coiners of ſuch falſe notions, and loudly cries out, <hi>wo unto thoſe that call evil good, and good evil.</hi> But to eſpouſe a while the cauſe of the injur'd Virtues, all which our falſe witneſs is ready to Swear into the Plot of our deſtruction; let us examine whether we have not much greater reaſon to rely upon them, as our only Bulwork and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, when they are placed in that Prince to whom he is pleaſed out of his exceſs of boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to grant them all, becauſe he could not deny him one, than to look upon them as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and pernicious, and as his own Evidence againſt them runs, <hi>The Inſtruments of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> Let us therefore allow him Fortitude, that which is the firſt in the rank of all the Virtues, and which ſtands there boldly in the front, as if deſign'd for the Protection of all the reſt; and without which a Prince is as contemptible in himſelf, as he is uſeleſſe to his People: Can a Nation be more bleſt than in the ſecurity which the matchleſſe Valour of ſuch a Prince ought in all reaſon to create? or can any man, that has the leaſt ſhare of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, entertain ſo vain an imagination, as to think that that invincible Courage which he has ſo often, and ſo eminently exerted in the defence of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> when they were his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Subjects, and when but his own ſingle ſhare of Glory redounded to himſelf, ſhould otherwiſe imploy it when advanced to a Throne, when all thoſe that he protects are his own People; when all the Renown ſhal be wholly His, when every Subjects<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Honour that he vindicats ſhal increaſe the luſtre of his own; and every <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man he ſaves, add to the largeneſſe of his Empire.</p>
            <p>But becauſe our Author maliciouſly ſuggeſts, that this Virtue may be imploy'd in making him more daring for the Cauſe of <hi>Rome;</hi> I would adviſe him to conſider, whether the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Fortitude in his Ethicks, (if he has ever read any,) be not as equally diſtant from Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merity and Raſhneſſe, as from Fear and Cowardice; and then whether the attempts of an impoſſible thing, (which as yet by his ſilence, he has allowed the introducing of Popery to be,) don't wholly overthrow that Virtue on which this very Suppoſition is built. He might alſo have been informed, that all the Virtues have ſo cloſe an Affinity between themſelves, and ſo near a dependance upon each other, that not one can act without the allowance of all the reſt; ſo that whatever is againſt Juſtice cannot be the object of Fortitude. If then he be a Man of Juſtice, this ſtill ſhould produce in Us the greater aſſurance that his Courage ſhal be no otherwiſe exerciſed, but for their Safety and Honour, to whom all his endeavours by all the Laws both Humane and Divine are moſt due; This will make him maintain the Juſt Rights of His people, to which by his Oath he will then be moſt ſolemnly and ſtrictly oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, much more inviolably than that imaginary Right of the Pope, which none can be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that he allows, and to which it is moſt certain he has no ſuch obligation, or ever was Sworn. Then if he be a Maſter of Temperance, what is that but a bridle upon all his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, a perpetual boſom Monitor that will withhold his hand, and allay his heat, that will curb the very firſt motions of Cruelty or Revenge, which the malice of his oppoſers might elſe have ſome grounds to fear? This is that Virtue to which we owe Pardons, and Acts of Oblivion, This is that which will make him aſcend the Throne, though never ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd, with the ſame Moderation and Clemency as did his Brother before him. Laſtly, if he has Prudence, that will teach him not to exaſperate a People of ſo ſtiff a neck, not to loſe the hearts of his Subjects for their difference of Opinion; that wil lay before him the many uſeful examples of thoſe Princes, that have unhappily ſtrove to change the ancient Laws of their Government, who endeavouring to remove the Old Land-Marks, have loſt their whole Poſſeſſions; who ſtriving to alter the building of the State to their own Humour, have brought down the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fabrick upon their heads, and periſhed in the ruine of their falling Kingdoms. Thus I thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, I have in ſome meaſure juſtified the four Moral Virtues from the ſevere charge of their being Inſtruments of our Deſtruction, not without ſome wonder, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137224:4"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndignation too, that any man ſhould ſpeak ſo ill of things he did not underſtand, or treat Strangers ſo uncivilly: For, indeed ſuch they are to our Author. Had he any Courage, he would have ſcorn'd to inſult over the preſent misfortune of the braveſt of Men; had he any Juſtice, he would not have appear'd ſo earneſt againſt that Succeſſion which is grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the Laws of God and Man; had he any Temperance, he would have ſpar'd his Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Invectives; and had he any Prudence, he would have burnt his Book, and ſaved the Hang-man a labour. But ſtay, let us be as favourable to him as we can, let us try if we can excuſe him, his ill treatment of the Virtues; perhaps he rail'd at them only to bring in his Quibble, and becauſe <hi>Cardo</hi> is Latin for a <hi>Hinge,</hi> therefore the Cardinal Virtues were to <hi>be the Hinges to open the Gates to Popery;</hi> or what if his Picque againſt them be, their having ſome Name-ſakes in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince his Friend <hi>Mirry Andrew,</hi> in that excellent piece of <hi>Smithfield</hi> Drollery, <hi>The Rehearſal Transproſed,</hi> has been pleaſed to call them, <hi>The red-hatted Virtues.</hi> Well, whatever his quarrel be, I am ſure His Royal Highneſs has reaſon to be not a little ſatisfied, to ſee that the defence of the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and Virtue it ſelf, is the ſame cauſe, and that whoever oppoſes the Juſtice of his Succeſſion, muſt forfeit his Morality as well as his Allegiance.</p>
            <p>But when the Notion of ſuch a Popiſh Succeſſor, ſuch a one as ſhall maintain the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the preſent Government, (and in that, the publick Worſhip of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is included) without any alteration, puzzles the Gentleman ſtrangely; <hi>Nor can he make it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſist with reaſon,</hi> no not he, <hi>nor with the least ſhadow of poſſibility.</hi> And where is the difficulty? where is the unreaſonableneſſe? Why forſooth, he muſt <hi>ſuppreſse the potent and dangerous Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that would deſtroy the Protestant Worſhip, Peace and Intereſt: And the Wiſdom of ſeveral ſucceſſive Monarchs, and a whole Nations unanimous prudence has declar'd Popiſh Priests to be theſe potent and dangerous enemies.</hi> Have they ſo? then there are Laws to ſecure us againſt them, then why are we in ſuch fear? Then what is left to any Monarch that Succeeds, but to execute the Laws he finds, derived down to him to maintain and preſerve, together with his Crown and Dignity? And ſince by the prudent zeal of both our Kings and People, our Religion has ſo ſtrong a fence built round about it, ſince this Vine is ſo hedged in, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Wild Boars out of the Wood can root it up, nor the little Foxes devour it; why do we torment our ſelves with any further diſquiet? why do we not rather ſit down under the ſhadow of it; and bleſs him whoſe right hand has planted it? <hi>But alas, under the Reign of an</hi> Engliſh <hi>Papiſt,</hi> the caſe will not be the ſame; <hi>But we ſhal be in much greater danger, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the multitude of their Roman Emiſſaries, and thoſe too embolden'd by hopes of connivance and mercy, and if ever the Proteſtant Religion want a Defender, it will be then.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly I am ſo far from thinking, that the Reign of a Popiſh King can be any way advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to the deſigns of the Jeſuitical Inſtruments, that I rather believe it will of neceſſity be the greateſt occaſion of their deſtruction; eſpecially ſince it is in the power of every Subject in the three Kingdoms to be a Defender of the Proteſtant Religion if it want it. And if people ſhal think ſo, as naturally then they will, to be ſure no Information, no Conviction of Recuſants, no Adminiſtration of Teſts or Oaths to the leaſt ſupected ſhal be wanting, no diligence ſpar'd which is backt by the Laws of the Land, which then more then ever will be waken'd againſt them, and which can't be diſpenſ'd withal, muſt needs be effectual to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruine of the whole party. This our Author himſelf ſeems to be ſenſible of, and to allow; and this is one of his <hi>pretty Chimaera's, and miſmatched incongruous Ingredients,</hi> as he ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly Phraſis it, <hi>that muſt go to make up the Compoſition of a Popiſh King;</hi> and can He then, or the moſt violent oppoſers of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> deſire any thing beyond this to gratifie their utmoſt malice upon the Members of that Church, than to be aſſured, that a Prince of that very Religion ſhal be the cauſe of their deſtruction? <hi>ſuis &amp; ipſa</hi> Roma <hi>viribus ruet.</hi> For indeed all this a <hi>Popiſh</hi> King muſt do, or ſuffer to be done, and all his Apology to them muſt be what the Pamphleteer ſays, <hi>We muſt expect to be made to us, He cannot help it,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 20.) <hi>He cannot help it,</hi> that is, if the Law will have it ſo, his duty is to ſee that the Law have its ccurſe; and whatever his private Opinion may be, whatever tenderneſſe he may bear to the very perſons he ſhal puniſh; yet to remember his obligation to the publick, ſo far as to give them up to the hands of Juſtice, with the ſame conſtancie of mind, with the ſame ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of the preſent, and commendation of all ſucceeding Ages, that the immortal <hi>Brutus</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd up his darling Sons to the Rods and Axes of the Lectors. This, had our Author con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:137224:4"/>he would not have ſo far betrayed his Morals, as to have ſtil'd a Prince, in every thing elſe brave to admiration, <hi>(abject and deplorable Coward,)</hi> for not daring to undertake either unlawful or impoſſible exploits, nor been ſo out of his Politicks, as to call governing by Law, <hi>ſneaking on a Throne.</hi> But alas! good man, he has a fit of kindneſſe on the ſuddain come upon him, he is infinitely concern'd for that <hi>Scene of war,</hi> and reſtleſs inquietudes ſuch a Prince <hi>muſt have within himſelf, who to spare a Fagget at</hi> Smithfield, <hi>muſt walk on hot Irons himſelf, and have only</hi> Good Friday <hi>entertainments on a Throne,</hi> and with ſuch like, no doubt prevailing pieces of Rehtorick, would perſwade us, that a Crown to him would be ſo uneaſie a thing, that he had better be without it. Alas, he would not have the Duke undergo that torment for all the world, not he; but this is only a flouriſh of his ſtile, in imitation I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of a Brother Sir <hi>Formal</hi> of his, <hi>who Laboured as much as he could, to prove, that the Bill was for the Duke's good,</hi> and undertook by dint of Argument to make it appear, that the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of His Royal Highneſs, was an Act of Grace.</p>
            <p>Let us come now to an Argument of ſome moment; and conſider what weight ſo ſolemn a Proteſtation and ſo ſacred an Oath as a King of <hi>England</hi> is obliged at his Coronation to take, is likely to have with a Prince that has any ſenſe at all either of Honour or Religion: Why truly our Characterizer ſays none at all, and tells us, <hi>That ſome can give us ſmart reaſons for it:</hi> He gives us but one; which we will examine and try, if we can produce as ſmart ones againſt it. <hi>If he keeps his Oath,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>we must allow that the only motive that prompts him to keep it, is ſome obligation that he believes is in an Oath;</hi> Yes, we will allow it, there is a double obligation of Nature and of Religion; Well, what then? <hi>but conſidering he is of a Religion that can abſolve Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from their Allegiance.</hi> And are you ſure he is of ſuch a Religion? We hear the <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> Proteſtations againſt that Doctrine daily ſounded in our Ears; we are told by many of them that they abominate the Poſition, and muſt needs be convinc'd, that granting many of the Doctors of their Church to be of that opinion; yet it is a Doctrine never univerſally receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that even they who believe, do not preach to all, and therefore very unlikely it is if they hide it from any, that it ſhould be uſed as a Bait for the Converſion of any Prince, from whom in all probability they would ſtudiouſly conceal ſuch a point, as would put him in danger of the loſs of his Kingdoms, as often as his holy Father the Pope ſhould be teaſty, or call him Heretick. Well, <hi>but conſidering him to be of ſuch a perſwaſion, why may not his Religion releaſe a King from his Faith to an Excommunicated and Heretical People?</hi> Ay! there's the miſchief on't, theſe <hi>Abſolutions</hi> and <hi>Diſpenſations,</hi> and <hi>Jeſuitical Loopholes</hi> can do any thing. But now let us a little conſider and weigh the probability of theſe poor ſhifts and evaſions, ever being made uſe of to our prejudice by his Royal Highneſs: Can it be believed, that He, who only out of the Conſcience that he made of an Oath, and the Obligation that he thought was in it, has already parted with the places of the greateſt Honour and Profit in the Kingdom, is ever likely to have a leſs Veneration for that moſt Religious one that he then muſt take? Or can we imagine, that if he thought any power whatever could abſolve him from ſuch a tye, he would ever have ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled at the ſwallowing that which he could with ſo much eaſe have diſgorged again? Eſpecially when ſuch a proceeding had removed all Suſpitions and Jealouſies concerning his Religion, and facilitated his way to the Throne, wherein he might eſtabliſh it before the people had warning enough to make any oppoſition. Had this been his Principle, then had been the time to make uſe of it, and the eaſie aſcent thereby to a Throne had been the beſt plea for his breach of Faith. Then if ever, it was neceſſary, for <hi>ſi violandum eſt jus regnandi, cauſa violandum eſt.</hi> But to <hi>ſtrengthen this Argument, our Author will give the World an inſtance of the power of an Oath with a</hi> Roman Catholick <hi>King.</hi> And that is, <hi>His moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, (the Famous Gentleman on the other ſide the water) who contrary to his Oath upon the Sacrament, has Invaded Flanders.</hi> And muſt all of that Religion be Vow breakers and Perjur'd, becauſe one Ambitious Prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e has vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated at once his Oath and his Religion too? Beſides, how far this Perjury of his is to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith, and how Zealous a Son he is of that Church, his quarrel even at this inſtant on foot with the Pope, is ſufficient to inform us. If a man has born in him thoſe Seeds of Ambition, and that Luſt of being Great, 'tis not the fault of the Religion that he profeſſeth, but the Viciouſneſs of his Nature that makes him ſacrifice his Conſcience to his Pride. If a man be naturally inclin'd to Virtue or Vice, let his Faith be what it will, his Morality will be the ſame; and he that has learnt from the great Law of Nature how Sacred the tye of an Oath ought to be, let him be in what Church he will, ſhall very hardly be brought to think that this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:137224:5"/>Gordian knot can be unty'd by every jugling Prieſt. Again, if Oaths will not bind <hi>Papiſts,</hi> if they come up as eaſily as they go down; why do we betray our folly ſo palpably as to think to ſecure our ſelves by adminiſtring them to <hi>Roman Catholicks?</hi> Why are the <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy</hi> Oaths tendered to them? and why do they refuſe them? Why are new Teſts devis'd that may be taken as harmleſly with a Diſpenſation in the Pocket, as the Mountebank does poiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with his Antidote by? Why is the Wiſdom of the whole Nation thus arraigned, and the High Court of Parliament it ſelf accuſed of the <hi>Goatham</hi> Policy, in building the Hedge to fence in the <hi>Cuckow:</hi> For this muſt be the very top of their ſage forecaſt, if they did not think that theſe Oaths did clip their Wings, as well as build the hedge about them: And that if they can do, not only the little ſuck-egge <hi>Cuckow Prieſt,</hi> but the Imperial Eagle it ſelf may be kept within the Fence.</p>
            <p>I deſign'd (in purſuance of my firſt undertaking) to be on the Defenſive part only, and not to have at all meddl'd with the oppoſite Faction; The Tale of <hi>Forty One</hi> and <hi>Forty Eight</hi> hath been long enough the Theme to be better made uſe of than it is. But here's an unlucky harrangue of our Author's, againſt Religion, immediately follows, that is enough to make the <hi>Old Rebellion</hi> riſe again, even out of its Grave of the <hi>Oblivion Act.</hi> I will therefore joyn with him in his railing at that deſperate Incendiary of all Nations, <hi>Religion:</hi> (I hope he means ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, and underſtands the pretence and maſque of it by that Name) as hearrily as himſelf; I will bring him in my ſhare of ends of Verſe, and ſayings of Phyloſophers; <hi>I'll</hi> muſter all <hi>Lucretius</hi>'s ſcraps againſt it; I can tell you of <hi>Tantum Religio,</hi> and <hi>Religio peperit ſceteroſa at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> impia facta;</hi> and all this I can make out too; Religion was the Goſpel-trumpet that firſt ſounded to Battel, and whetted our Fears and Jealouſies into Courage and Rebellion; Religion, that firſt kindled the Flame, maintained it with Fuel; The <hi>Fight againſt the Lords Anointed</hi> began ſtill with a Pſalm, and ended with a Hymn; Religion was the Song; Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was the burden of <hi>The Holy Ballad ſingers,</hi> when the <hi>Scots</hi> came tweedling it over, <hi>with the praiſe of God in their mouths, and a Two edged ſword in their hands.</hi> No matter then, if we mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t be ruined, whether St. <hi>Ambroſe's</hi> or <hi>Robert wiſdom's Te Deum</hi> be ſung for the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, whether the holy <hi>to Peean</hi> goes to <hi>David's,</hi> or to <hi>Nero's</hi> Harp, to the <hi>Church Organ,</hi> or to the <hi>Scotch Bagpipe.</hi> And ſee, our Author is already at it; he's ſounding a Parliament-Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies <hi>Epinicium,</hi> or rather holding forth in a Thankſgiving-Sermon, and in the inſulting Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the proſperous villany of the late times crying out, <hi>To vow and Covenant, and with a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League forſwear three Kingdoms out of their Liberties and Lives; that's Illustrious and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick: There's Glory in great Atchievements, and Virtue in Succeſs: Come on then! Let us the mighty</hi> Nimrods <hi>hunt for Noble Spoils, and fly at a whole Nation, Property and Inheritance.</hi> That is as he explains himſelf in the 29 page. <hi>Let us never leave, till we have hunted the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Lyon down.</hi> But how he's out of breath, and his Glaſſe is run, and therefore ſo much for this time.</p>
            <p>But now to the main Objection: <hi>Some People will tell us,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>That 'tis wholly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any</hi> Popiſh Succeſſor, <hi>by all his Arts and Endeavours whatſoever, to introduce</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery <hi>into</hi> England. Yes indeed will they tell you ſo again; For if you remember, they told you ſo already, in the ſecond page of your Pamphlet, and indeed I am of opinion, that it ought then to have been conſidered; for till you had remov'd this bar of impoſſibility out of the way, I ſee but very little hopes of making any further progreſs, <hi>that you could reaſonably have.</hi> This argument lay before you juſt as you ſet out; and being ſenſible that this muſt be o're-paſſed before you could proceed in your journey, you came on indeed with very great briſkneſſe and aſſurance, as if you deſign'd to have leapt the Ditch; but your heart fail'd, and made the Cowardly <hi>Rhodian</hi> boggle juſt upon the brink: But now, ſince you are forc'd to it, and neceſſity has given you courage to take the leap, it is ſome pleaſure to the ſtanders by to ſee you fallen in the midſt of it, and ſo plung'd in the mire, as not to be in any viſible liklyhood of getting out. But let us ſee how the poor ſunder'd Jad ſtruggles to work it ſelf out of the Bog. <hi>If he's a Papist that ſays ſo, he knows he believes his Conſcience; for our late</hi> Helliſh Plot <hi>is a plain demonſtration, that their whole party believed it poſſible.</hi> Now the ſport of it is, this flouncing noes but make him ſtick the faſter. For what if he that ſays ſo, be <hi>as good a Proteſtant as the Author,</hi> as I am ſure a great many are, that both ſay and believe ſo too? why then, they may ev'n ſay ſo, and believe ſo ſtill for all him: He has nothing to ſay to the contrary, unleſſe they are Papiſts th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſay ſo; and for them, mark how ſhrewdly he is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:137224:5"/>provided. Firſt, he gives, them the Lie, and juſtifies it thus; <hi>Their whole party believe it poſſible,</hi> and therefore it was poſſible, for ſo he muſt infer, if he means to prove any thing againſt the foregoing Argument. And is it ſo then Mr. Characterizer? becauſe they believed it poſſible, therefore was it ſo? Come, come, you are a dangerous Man, and I wiſh people knew you, that they might have a care of you: You, forſooth, (under the notion of running down a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſion</hi>) are proving the verity of the <hi>Popiſh Faith,</hi> and aſſerting every thing to be true that's believ'd by a <hi>Papist.</hi> Well, I am glad I have found out our Scribler, for none could ſure have written ſuch ſtuff, but a <hi>diſguiſed Prieſt,</hi> or at leaſt, a <hi>Papist in Maſquerade.</hi> But after all, granting the Belief of a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> that the introducing of <hi>Popery</hi> was ſo feaſible, according to our Author's opinion, to be a certain argument that it was ſo, and that this was once the Belief of the whole party, yet how does it follow that it is ſo ſtill? If they be that cunning and politick People as he ſoon after ſays they are, I am ſure they have very little reaſon to think that that Deſign, which was in ſo hopeful a forwardneſſe, as never ſince Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days could be boaſted of, carried on with all the Art and Contrivance, all the Sec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and Cunning of a moſt diligent and active Party, favoured by ſeveral of the greateſt Perſons of the Kingdom, and thoſe moſt eminent for their Riches and Intereſt, to ſupport the Cauſe, the univerſal ſecurity of the whole Nation, that then not ſo much as dreamt of the Mine that was ready to take Fire, Conſpiring together with thoſe Sons of darkneſs, in the great work of our Deſtruction; and yet, after all this, was brought to nought, ſhould ever at all (or at leaſt in this Age) be effected, when all their meaſures are broken, and all their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked contrivances laid open, and the whole Scence of that Religious Villany diſplayed to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick view, when the whole Nation is ſtill kept awake with continual Fears, and freſh Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larms againſt them, while the very meaneſt of the people are as diligent in this cauſe, as the great ones that deſcend to joyn with 'm in it, and when (to prevent any ſurpriſe from the <hi>Pope</hi> or the <hi>Gaul</hi>) there's not a <hi>Gooſe</hi> but cackles for the preſervation of our Capitol. Alas! ſuch projects as theſe, when once diſcover'd, are for that age defeated; and when ſo great a deſign is to be hatcht a new, it ripens as ſlowely as <hi>China</hi> does, that muſt be buried a Age un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ground before it comes to perfection, and than too is very often as brittle as that, and as eaſie to be daſhed in pieces. Thus we ſee how impoſſible a thing it is, that in the temper which now runs quite through the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, that Idolatrous Superſtition ſhould ever be here re-eſtabliſhed, which by ſo unanimous a conſent of ſo many of our wiſeſt Princes, and all our people, has been rooted out from among us. But is not the people of <hi>England</hi> highly beholding to our Author, that in this ſeeming difficulty has found an expedient for the introducing of it again? This Sir <hi>Pol</hi> of ours is a notable Head-piece, let him alone, and we ſhal ſee as ſhrewd a piece of contrivance, as the bringing over an Army that ſhal croſs the Narrow Seas dry-foot by the help of Cork-ſhoes. Let us ſee this project of ſetting up <hi>Popery;</hi> Why, firſt <hi>the foundation of it muſt be laid,</hi> O'my word that's but reaſonable, and the firſt Foundation of <hi>Popery is Arbitrary Government.</hi> Ay marry Sir, now he ſays ſomewhat, only make this an Arbitrary Government, a ſmal piece of buſineſs, a trifle that; and then <hi>Popery</hi> follows as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally as the Fox's body did, when he had got his head in at the hole.</p>
            <p>But muſt this be done? Why, <hi>Wou'd be</hi> ſhal tell you, <hi>If a Papiſt reign, we very well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that the Sheriffs, Juſtices of the Peace, and all the Judiciary Officers are of the King's Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Yes; and are they not ſo when a <hi>Protestant</hi> reigns? Yet even ſuch a Prince whoſe Religion does not in the leaſt render him obnoxious to his people, but whoſe conſent with them in the firſt and chiefeſt duty of humane Life, the Divine Worſhip, ſhould rather make both Prince and People of <hi>one Soul, and one Mind;</hi> Let him have all the advantages, not only which a <hi>Papiſt</hi> muſt of neceſſity loſe, but which a <hi>Protestant</hi> may wiſh or imagine, would find it ſo difficult a taſk to ſet up for this Arbitrary way of Government, which our Author makes ſo eaſie a piece of buſineſſe, that I ſhal not need to tell the conſequence of ſuch an Attempt, ſince the impoſſibility of ſucceeding in it will never ſuffer it to be made. If then <hi>Arbitrary Power be the Foundation of Popery,</hi> there is very little fear of ever ſeeing that great Idol rear'd, whoſe Baſis can never be laid. And of this we ſhall be ſo much the ſurer under the Reign of a <hi>Popiſh King,</hi> by how much leſs opportunities he will have to ſet up this new Model, and by how much greater oppoſition, and indefatigable diligence, and watchful ſuſpicion, the whole Nation will imploy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Horſe, <hi>Arbitrary Government,</hi> big with <hi>Popery</hi> and our <hi>utter</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:137224:6"/>is too narrow for its reception) and afterwards admit it into the Pallace.</p>
            <p>'Tis not in the power of Sheriffs, Juſtices of the Peace, or of Judges, let them be as corrupt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, or of as <hi>baſe a Conſtitution,</hi> as our Author would have 'em, to work ſo extraordinary a change: For if they are of <hi>baſe Constitutions,</hi> as he phraſes it, the hopes of perferment on one hand ſhal not work upon 'em, ſo far as the fear of puniſhment on the other; nor will they be like to uſe the Laws with the Cruelty of <hi>Procruſtes,</hi> who muſt needs by experience be aſſur'd that our Countrey does not want thoſe Publick-ſpirited Patriots, who with the Juſtice and Strength of <hi>Theſeus,</hi> can make 'em ſuffer by their own Barbarity. Nay, how great an influence this fear of diſobliging the people, has over low Spirits, even in the higheſt Offices, we have very freſh inſtances; When, by ſome of 'em, even Juſtice has been denied, where it might give diſtest to the Repreſentatives of the Nation.</p>
            <p>This is indeed indeed an action very unaccountable, but ſufficient to make it appear to the World, how much ſtronger the Peoples Intereſt and Party is, than any Popiſh Princes can ever be, by how much more formidable that is than this, even to the Tribunal of Juſtice it ſelf, which ſhould never fear. If this then will not do the work, <hi>and the Pope is not abſolute, there wants a ſtanding Army to Crown the work: And he ſhall have it.</hi> Shall he ſo Sir? O'my word we are much obliged to you, for granting a ſtanding Army; but ſtay, he comes off with, <hi>who ſhal hinder him?</hi> Nay, that's another matter; then pray Mr. <hi>Bayes,</hi> be pleaſed to inform us, where is this ſtanding Army, is it in diſguiſe? &amp; does it lie concealed as your tother did at <hi>Knights-bridge?</hi> Indeed, indeed that's dangerous, for an Army in diſguiſe is full as bad, nay, much worſe than a <hi>Papist</hi> in Maſquerade. But yet I have ſome hopes, that ſince this <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> Succeſſor has not travel'd the Rod ſo much as others, has not been ſo great a Journey-taker about <hi>England,</hi> nor made ſo many <hi>Weſtern</hi> Progreſſes, the Inn-keepers will not be ſo much his Friends as to hide all his Horſe and Foot, and Ammunition, and other odd things that go with an Army; and then all this great project is like to be defeated, and fall to nothing. Or, if this Army is not yet raiſ'd, and don't lye hid in the place we were talking of, or in the Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in <hi>Worſterſhire,</hi> how ſhal it be raiſ'd: You know, you have told the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Succeſſor, <hi>that he ſhal have a ſtanding Army,</hi> and I'le aſſure you he will expect you ſhould be as good as your word. Why then, <hi>if you would have this Army quietly raiſ'd, ſome honourable pretences muſt be found:</hi> Truly that is well thought on, for if that had been forgot, and Drums had beat up through the City for Voluntiers to ſet up Arbitrary Power and <hi>Popery,</hi> it is ten to one but all the Fat had been in the Fire. Well let us get a pretence then, and when we have one, if it be only a pretence, though never ſo Right Honourable, Suppoſe the People ſhould ſmell it out, and be very unwilling to be raiſ'd for any thing but their own defence: This were indeed ſomewhat like Rebelling, but not quite ſo improbable, but that a wiſe Prince would foreſee, and avoid it, and we may very well ſuppoſe it. <hi>Suppoſe, quoth, a, I am not at all mortified at your ſuppoſe, not I, Sir, I tell you if we have a Popiſh Succeſsor, he ſhall bring in a ſtanding Army, and that ſtanding Army ſhall bring in Arbitrary Power, and Arbitrary Power bring in Popery, and then what becomes of your Suppoſe? Suppoſe quoth</hi> a? — Mr. <hi>Bayes,</hi> I beg your pardon for offending you, I am convicn'd, <hi>I</hi> yeild, and muſt own, that though you have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced <hi>Popery</hi> with ſo much eaſe, you are the only man in the world that could have ſo brought things about, and deſerve to be General at leaſt of that Army, which you have been at the whole trouble of raiſing.</p>
            <p>But enough of this trifling; let us be a little Serious, and leave off our Laughter, which cou'd not be avoided in Diſcourſe with this impertinent, grave conceited <hi>Politico,</hi> this flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Oratorical <hi>Buffoon,</hi> with his <hi>Ragioni de Stato</hi> of Sr. <hi>Poll,</hi> dreſt up in the Eloquence of Sir <hi>Formal.</hi> There is none can be ſo great a Stranger to the Affairs of this Countrey, as not to ſee how ſtrong the Tide runs againſt <hi>Popery;</hi> a Tide ſo impetuous, ſo ſtrengthened and ſwell'd up with the flowing in of almoſt all Intereſts againſt it, that it can never be ſtem'd by the ſmal reſiſtance that the moſt vigorous Prince can make in the head of ſo ruin'd, ſo weak and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable a party; 'twere folly to attempt it, and extream madneſs to hope to effect it. So young as the Reformation was in the Reign of Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> it might indeed with ſome eaſe be pluckt up e're it had taken root, or ſpread it ſelf over half the Kingdom: The number of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in thoſe days being equal at leaſt, if not exceeding that of Proteſtants, &amp; they (as in all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we muſt allow) all longing for the reſtoration of their Religi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that this Idolatrous
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137224:6"/>and ſo ſtrongly rooted in the reigns of four moſt Religious and prudent Princes; the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſo firmly eſtabliſhed, and that as much by the purity of its Doctrine, the decency of its Diſcipline, and the Innocency of its Principles, as by the Authority of the publick, and the Laws of the Land. The <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church ſo deteſted, both for the dangerous Innovations of its Doctrines, and the Idolatry of its Ceremonies, and ſo odious in the eyes of the people, for its pernitious principles expreſt in the Villanous practices of its Profeſſors, in Maſſacres and plots, all detected, and at laſt defeated, to their utter confuſion that ingaged in them: Things <hi>I</hi> ſay, being in this ſtate, it would be a greater Miracle than the moſt Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Legends of that Church has yet to boaſt of, ſhould it ever be reſtored in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And this our Author himſelf well enough knows; for though he would perſwade the people all along that <hi>Popery</hi> is juſt coming in, yet this falſe Satyr can blow cold and hot with with the ſame Breath, and can't help owning, <hi>That the ſtubborn</hi> Engliſh <hi>Genius will not bend to the Superſtitions of</hi> Rome, (p. 39.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus far our Author tells you, he has given you the Portraiture of</hi> a <hi>Popiſh King;</hi> and indeed it is well he tells you ſo, for he has drawn ſuch a horrid Figure, ſo Monſtrous and diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd a piece, that it was but reaſon that he ſhould write under the Picture, <hi>This is a Popiſh King</hi> that we might know what to make of it. <hi>And now he is for taking a draught of his Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in his Minority, while he is only Heir apparent;</hi> and this he performs with ſuch fine touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and maſter-ſtroaks, that you may eaſily perceive it to be the ſame hand.</p>
            <p>And here for three or four pages we have him only <hi>Imagining then,</hi> and <hi>Imagining likewiſe,</hi> and <hi>Suppoſing now,</hi> and <hi>Suppoſing likewiſe,</hi> and <hi>ſuppoſing moreover,</hi> at ſo extravagant and wild a rate, that his Brain muſt be very hot that can keep pace with him in his mad carreer of Fancie. We may only obſerve, that in his over-haſty zealous fits of imagination, he forgets himſelf often, ſo far as to betray the very grand ſecret of the party, the ground of all their Popular railing at <hi>Popery,</hi> and that is no other than their being weary of <hi>Monarchy.</hi> This is the colour for all the cry againſt Kingly Government, and Right Succeſſion; and as he tells you, that is that makes the <hi>Subjects knee ſo ſtiff and ſo ſtubborn; this makes them in ſtudying to prevent Tyrrany, grow jealous of Monarchy; this is that which makes them ſo far from ſupplying the real and moſt preſſing neceſſities of His Majeſty, that they triumph in his greateſt wants even when his neareſt Safety</hi> (mark that) <hi>calls for their Aſſiſtance;</hi> And this is that which in the Language of the late Addreſſe gives pretence to that Inſolent Threat of <hi>breaking the whole Chain of Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Succeſſion in pieces,</hi> (p. 23.) So that 'tis plain, though the triple Mitre is ſtruck at, the three Crowns is their aim, nor would they be ſo violent againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> which they can have no ground to be afraid of, unleſſe, by very freſh experience, they knew thatthait was the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful charm to bring the people to the ruine of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> which by this only means is to be deſtroyed: knowing the multitude to be not unlike the Beaſts or Cattle in the Hold of a ſhip, which in any Storm that is raiſ'd, if they are made apprehenſive of the Veſſel ſinking on the one ſide, run immediatly with ſuch a violent panick fear to the other, that they over-ſet the Ship, and quite overwhelm both themſelves and it in ruine and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Come we now to the next Argument, which he ſayes a Critick will make uſe of. <hi>Suppoſe this</hi> Popiſh <hi>Heir undoubtedly believes, that there is no way to Heaven but his own, ſhould any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon earth make him to renounce his Principles of Chriſtianity?</hi> Why truly I am ſo far of this Criticks mind, as he calls him, that I ſhould think it very unreaſonable that the Prince alone ſhould not have the benefit of Liberty of Conſcience, which every Subject in his Dominions takes very ill to have deny'd to himſelf. But he goes on, <hi>And then if all the grievances of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom lye at his door, 'tis his unhappineſs, and not his fault.</hi> Very right, if ſome F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctious Spirits ſet the Nation on a flame, and then firſt cry out Fire, and convey their Fire-Balls into his Pockets, if they make us miſerable, and then lay it at his door, 'tis his unhappineſs indeed, but not his fault. But ſee what uſe our Author makes of this: And ſo ſayes he, <hi>When this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Heir comes to the Crown, and promotes the</hi> Romiſh <hi>Interest with all the Severity, Injuſtice, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Religious Cruelty can invent</hi> — Hold, hold, not ſo faſt: You are an excellent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putant, whoſe ſtrongeſt Argument is begging the Queſtion. You take for granted that all this <hi>Severity, and Injustice, and Tyranny, and Religious Cruelty</hi> ſhall be then exerciſed, and are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth chiefly employed in finding out an excuſe to put into this Princes mouth for doing ſo; and you have furniſht him with a notable one; <hi>His Anſwer will be, he cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly it.</hi> Come, come, ſpeak your Conſcience, do you really believe this will be his Anſwer? Yes; a Prince
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:137224:7"/>who can do all theſe mighty things, and act with ſo Arbitrary and unbounded a power as muſt be neceſſary to enable him to all this, after all his Severity, and Injuſtice, and Cruelty, ſhall cry <hi>Peccavi</hi> to his people, with the School-Boys Apology, <hi>Indeed I could not help it.</hi> But ſuch ſtuff as this may be allowable to our Mr. <hi>Bayes,</hi> that ſeems to have very little knowledge of any Kings but thoſe of <hi>Branford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, but to make us amends, we have him immediatly exerciſing his Talent in a moſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetick piece of Rhetorick againſt <hi>Merit,</hi> and truly he is in the right of it: For merit I am ſure is never like to do him a kindneſs; and then preſently follows as ſharp a fit of Railing at the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, a Topick that I can't chooſe but confeſs my ſelf extreamly delighted with, eſpecially when handled by our Author, who manages it ſo dexterouſly, that all his Invectives againſt that, fall as heavy upon the turbulent <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and ſo wounds two of our moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous enemies at once. For thus he deſcribes <hi>Popery,</hi> (ſhall I ſay) or <hi>Presbytery! A Religion that does not go altogether in the old faſhion, Apoſtolical way of Preaching, and Praying, and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Nations, but ſcourging, and wracking, and broiling them in the fear of God: A Religion that for its own Propagation will at any time authorize its Champion to divest themſelves of their humanity, and act worſe than Devils to be Saints.</hi> If a man were to tranſverſe this Character of Religion, could he do it more appoſitly than in theſe Lines of <hi>Hudibras.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Twas</hi> Presbyterian <hi>true Blew,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For he was of that stubborn Crew,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of Errant Saints, whom all men grant,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To be the true Church Militant.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Such as build their Faith upon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Holy Text of Pike and Gun:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Decide all Controverſies by</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Infallible Artillery.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And prove their Doctrine Orthodox,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By Apoſtolick Blows and</hi> Knocks.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Call Fire and Sword, and Deſolation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A goodly-throw-Reformation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Well, after this ſhort breathing, upon a Subject, which he, nor any body elſe can ever want ſome fine ſhrewd thing or other to ſay, he proceeds thus; <hi>I, but (ſay the wiſeſt Criticks we have met with yet) if theſe be the dangers of a Popiſh</hi> King, <hi>why, have we not ſuch ſtrong, ſuch potent Laws made before this</hi> Popiſh Heir <hi>come to the Crown, that it ſhall be impoſſible for him ever to ſet up</hi> Popery, <hi>though he ſhould never ſo much endeavour it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed I am mightily rejoyced at our Author's unexpected civility, in allowing this to be the expedient of the wiſeſt Critick he has met with yet, for 'tis no leſs a Perſon than His moſt Sacred Majeſties own Propoſal and gracious Offer to his two Houſes of Parliament, in thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Declarations that he has made to 'em, of his moſt vigorous aſſiſtance in this wiſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the good of poſterity: An act becoming both the Juſtice and the Goodneſs of ſuch a King, that will neither debar his Brother from that Right by which himſelf reigns, nor leave his people in danger of the loſs of their deareſt and moſt ſacred Birth-rights, their liberty and Religion. But let us hear what our Politician ſays to this: <hi>I anſwer</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>To endeavour to ſet up</hi> Popery <hi>by Law, even with the Laws that we have against it, is impoſsible,</hi> p. 21. But if you remember, Sir, no further off than the 13th. page; <hi>You were afraid that even the Proteſtant Laws themſelves might be made to open the first Gate to Slavery, and ſo to Popery, by the help of thoſe</hi> Procruſteſe's <hi>that you were there talking of.</hi> And granting this, it would not be ſo impolitick as piece of work to make ſuch other Proteſtant Laws, that ſhould not be poſſibly ſhorten'd or ſtretch'd by e're a <hi>Procustes</hi> of 'em all, and then this projection will not deſerve to be accus'd of <hi>Nonſenſe.</hi> Nay we have your ſelf preſently confeſſing, <hi>that a</hi> Popiſh King <hi>may be totally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd from all power of introducing popery, by the force of ſuch Laws as may be made to tie up his hands.</hi> And who is ſo unreaſonable as to deſire any more? Surely <hi>Romes Dagon,</hi> (as elſewhere you phraſe it) will not be ſo formidable, when like that <hi>Aegyptian</hi> one of old, both its hands
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:137224:7"/>ſhall be broken off, and the power of hurting the true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> the Church of <hi>England,</hi> wholly taken away. Ay, <hi>but then theſe Laws muſt be ſuch as muſt ruine his Prerogative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This does not neceſſarily follow, and I believe His Majeſty (in His own Princely Wiſdom, and by His Councils Advice) was well enough ſatisfied that ſuch Laws might be made, as might not quite ruine the prerogative of his Succeſſor, tho' they might abate much of his power, in matters relating to the <hi>protestant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, granting even thus much, what you infer from this is doubly ridiculous. Firſt, <hi>That no Monarch would thus entail that effeminacy on a Crown, as ſhall render the Imperial Majeſty of</hi> England <hi>but a pageant, a meer puppet upon a Wire.</hi> For theſe Laws that bind up a King ſo ſtricct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuppoſe him <hi>a popiſh King,</hi> ſuch only being to be reſtrained; This is not therefore an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail'd Effeminacy, but rather a ſhort eclipſing of the full Splendor of a Crown, which in the next <hi>proteſtant Succeſſor</hi> is to ſhine forth with the greater Luſtre for its former obſcurity. And ſecondly, conſidering none but a <hi>Popiſh King,</hi> is thus to be limited, Is it not fooliſh enough that you ſhould here be offended at the ſmalneſs of his power, that would have him utterly debarr'd the Throne, aed ſo have no power at all.</p>
            <p>As for this Statute, that ſeems to make ſuch a bluſter, with the Tall Capital-Letters at the top, it is as little to his purpoſe as any thing that he ſays; For even the ſtrictneſs of that reaches none but thoſe that are <hi>lawfuly Convicted,</hi> and therefore concerns not his <hi>R. H.</hi> or if it did, the diſpute being about the Right of Succeſſion, and no ſucceſſion to the Crown being poſſible till after the Death of the predeceſſor, this at that time can be no obſtacle to the next Heir, when (according to the whole tenour of the Law) <hi>all Attainders ceaſe.</hi> Therefore, to urge more forcibly the Excluſion of the Duke, he is inſinuating to the people, <hi>That if ever a papiſt mounts this Throne, then all their petitions, proteſtings and Aſſociation-Votes will be remembred to purpoſe.</hi> That is exactly <hi>Catiline: The ills that we have done cannot be ſafe, but by attempting greater.</hi> But I am ſure there are ſome men have reaſon to remember, that a King that has had the greateſt oppoſition has been the moſt gracious Prince that ever reign'd, and been ſo far from <hi>remembring to purpoſe</hi> the Traytors that oppos'd him, that he has forgot 'em, even by Act of <hi>Parliament.</hi> So far is it from being generally true what he ſays. <hi>That he who has gone a long and tireſom journey through Brakes and Briars, to a ſplendid pallace, will be ſure to ſend out to root 'em up.</hi> That the laſt inſtance that we have had of ſuch a caſe makes it appear, that even thoſe little pliable Brambles &amp; Briars that bent and yielded to every blaſt, let it blow from what quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it would; and thoſe Brakes and Thorns that ſtuck ſo ſharply in the ſides of Majeſty; have not only been retriev'd from their due fate of being utterly rooted up, but been admitted into the palace it ſelf, and made to vie with, and indeed almoſt to over-top the talleſt Cedars them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that with unſhaken conſtancy did partake in the ſufferings of the Royal Cauſe, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bending, withſtood the force of the whole Storm.</p>
            <p>But now follows a very wiſe Diſcourſe againſt the <hi>Right of Succeſſion;</hi> and to prove that not to be ſo inviolable as ſome vehemently aſſert, we are referred to our own Chronicles. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, Sir, what 'tis you are Diſcourſing of; the <hi>Right of Succeſſion,</hi> as I take it, and then you ſhall refer me whither you pleaſe. Well then, I take up my Chronicle and fall a read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and there indeed I find ſome Kings Murther'd, and ſome Depoſ'd, the true Heir ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times depriv'd of his Succeſſion, by the power of a more prevailing Pretender to the ſame Right, the Crown bandied about between the Factions of two Houſes, laying equal claim to it, and ſcarce ever firmly ſettled for any conſiderable date of years. But all this while I am learnt to diſtinguiſh between <hi>matter of Fact</hi> and <hi>matter of Right,</hi> and know that they are very often oppoſite one to another; and that no precedent can alter the Nature of an unjuſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or make it allowable now, becauſe contrary to right it was done ſome hundred years ago. I am ſure the known Statutes of the Land ought to be the Rule of our Duty and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, rather than our Chronicles; men being to be govern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by Law, and not by Hiſtory. And as for thoſe Acts of Parliament which we find ordering and diſpoſing of the Succeſſion, we ſhal ſee how little they make for the purpoſe, for which they are produced. We muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore note, that all theſe Acts of Parliament, both of <hi>Henrie VIII.</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> are not made at all to alter the Right of Succeſſion: far from it, my, rather to eſtabliſh it; for they are only deſign'd to declare in whom this <hi>Right of Succeſſion</hi> was, and therefore were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed neceſſary, both in the times of <hi>H. VIII.</hi> (whoſe <hi>often Marriage and Divorces, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainder of his Wives;</hi> might make his Right diſputable among his Children) and in Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabath's</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:137224:8"/>time, who being without Iſſue, had ſeveral others that pretended to the Right of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſceding her. Theſe Acts of <hi>Parliament</hi> (I ſay) were abſolutely neceſſary, when the Title of the Crown might be dubious, but for the ſame reaſon very ridiculouſly and weakly urged, when it is clear to the blindeſt Apprehenſions, who is the true Succeſſor.</p>
            <p>After this notable bout of Law, and a few Statutes and Acts of <hi>Parliament,</hi> borrow'd from come Caſe-ſplittor or another; for his ſtile (for all its dulneſs) is too florid for a Lawyers; He is fluſht enough to think that he may venture to fall upon that which he calls <hi>the ſtrongest Argument</hi> for Succeſſion, <hi>If the Son of a private Gentleman, tho' a Papist, ſhall inherit, and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly poſſeſs his Hereditary Eſtate, is it not hard, nay barbarous Injuſtice, that the Son of a King, and Heir of a Crown, ſhould loſs his Patrimony of three Kingdoms for being a Papiſt?</hi> Indeed I muſt confeſs that in my opinion it is very hard, barbarous and unjuſt, eſpecially when ſuch proviſion ſhall be made that we may not be in danger of ſuffering any thing by his Opinion. But our Author ſayes <hi>we are in danger of this;</hi> and I ſay no; and ſo I find this at the bottom no more than the former Argument concerning the poſſibility of <hi>Arbitrary Government</hi> and <hi>Popery</hi> ever coming in upon us. And this I think has ſufficiently been conſidered in its place.</p>
            <p>I can't chooſe but ſmile at the next undertaking of our Sir <hi>Formal,</hi> who I perceive has the vanity to believe his Rhetorick can do any thing: He has therefore ſpun out a moſt fine <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue,</hi> to perſwade the Duke to quit (of his own accord) his pretention to a Crown, and indeed as to that I have little to anſwer, but muſt leave it to be as his Royal Highneſs and he ſhall agree upon the matter: Only I muſt by the way take notice of one of the Arguments he makes uſe of to this purpoſe, and try if I can make it as ſerviceable to another. If then (p. 30.) <hi>the little diſparity of their years be conſidered, and the diſtance and uncertainty of the Duke's ever coming to the Crown duely weighed,</hi> ſurely thoſe men are highly culpable, nay, the greateſt Enemies of the publick good that can be imagined; who thus for an uncertainty ruine <hi>a Kingdoms Peace and Proſperity,</hi> and make us run into thoſe ills which we are ſure to ſuffer, in avoiding that which we neither know, or are certain we ſhall be ever ſo much as in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of.</p>
            <p>There is another very remarkable paſſage in this laſt Diſcourſe, which (for its extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary quaintneſs of expreſſion, and delicacy of ſtile) ought by no means to eſcape us. It is a ſtory of a noble <hi>Roman,</hi> who, by the deſcription that he makes of him, can be the pattern of no other than the moſt deſervedly beloved Darling of the People, and who might, for ought we know, do our Nation as much ſervice in the ſame kind as the other did: He is thus therefore deſcribed in blank Heroick Meeter, as the dignity of this Subject required.</p>
            <q>
               <l>When a long Plague had reign'd in <hi>Rome,</hi> an Earth-quake</l>
               <l>Had open'd a prodigious Gulph in the</l>
               <l>Midſt of the <hi>Forum;</hi> their conſulted Oracle</l>
               <l>Told'm, That neither ſhould the Plague be stopp'd,</l>
               <l>Nor the breach clos'd, till the moſt Noble Victum</l>
               <l>In <hi>Rome</hi> appeas'd their angry Deity.</l>
               <l>When <hi>Curtius,</hi> a Noble Youth of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O' th' best and Highest <hi>Roman</hi> Quality,</l>
               <l>Princely adorn'd and mounted gallantly</l>
               <l>On Horſeback, with a look ſo gay, ſo cheerfull,</l>
               <l>More like a Bridegroom than a Sacrifice,</l>
               <l>Amidst a thouſand wondring tender Eyes</l>
               <l>Of all his Friends, the Rabble round about him,</l>
               <l>Rode headlong down into the yawning Pit.</l>
               <bibl>pag. 19.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Whoever can gueſs by this lively deſcription of the Authors, who our <hi>Engliſh Curtius,</hi> this Charmer of the People, this Gallant perſon ſo bravely mounted, and ſo like a Bridegroom is, would do very well to uſe what intereſt he can to perſwade him to do as noble an Action as the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Curtius</hi> did, and try whether by his being a Sacrifice, our Plague that Reigns among us would ceaſe: But if this <hi>Curtius</hi> can't be found out, to be even with our Author I will tell him a ſtory ſomewhat like his; and tho' poſſibly not in ſuch exactneſs of Meeter, yet as true,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137224:8"/>and of as good Authority as that, deſiring him and his Friends to conſider of it, becauſe I have a fancy that <hi>Moſes,</hi> in this caſe, is likely to give as good Inſtruction as <hi>Livy.</hi> There were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain turbulent Spirits among the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that had ſtirred up the people to rebel againſt their Guide <hi>Moſes,</hi> and their High-Prieſt <hi>Aaron,</hi> which was then all their <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> Upon this the <hi>Earth opened a Prodigious Gulph</hi> in the midſt of their Tents; but here one ſingle Victim would not ſatisfie, neither would the mouth of the Earth (that was open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) be content with leſs than the Ring-leaders of the Sedition, with all that adhered unto 'em, who together <hi>went down quick into the Pit;</hi> (Numb. 16. v. 30.) and ſo as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſays, <hi>The Earth opened, and ſwallowed up</hi> Dathan, <hi>and covered the Congregation of</hi> Abiram.</p>
            <p>And now I think we are at laſt come to that which is indeed <hi>Ratio ultima,</hi> and find our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor juſtifying the Rebellion of Subjects againſt their Prince; An Argument which I take the puhlick Miniſters of Juſtice more concerned to anſwer than my ſelf; for he who don't know <hi>who the Lords anointed is, and who is his Native Soveraign,</hi> (p. 31.) in my opinion ought no otherwiſe to be convinc'd. But becauſe at laſt he is for <hi>ſumming up all,</hi> (p. 34.) Let us ſee what is the utmoſt ſtrength of his reaſons for Rebellion; why that is this, <hi>That a Popiſh King is guilty of a greater ſin in bringing in Popery and Tyranny, than the People that takes up Arms againſt him,</hi> (p. 34.) is not this excellent arguing; ſuppoſing even this Propoſition to be true? Becauſe a Prince is guilty of a ſin; muſt the people be guilty of another? Ay, but he is guilty of a greater than they: Suppoſe then a Prince ſhould commit Inceſt, may his people by this be warranted to commit Adultery or Fornication, becauſe their ſin is not as big his? Or to our purpoſe, if a Prince be enticed into the <hi>Witchcraft of</hi> Rome, as our Author elſewhere calls it, will this Authorize the Peoples Rebellion, which the Scripture tells us is mighty like that very ſin, the ſin of <hi>Witchcraft?</hi> This is ſo abſurd and ſo fooliſh a defence of ſo abominable and pernicious a Poſition, as deſerves both the Rods ad Axes of the Magiſtrate, the Rod for <hi>the Fools back,</hi> and the Ax for <hi>the Traytors head,</hi> if it be not too great an Honour.</p>
            <p>And now becauſe the writer of the <hi>Popiſh Character</hi> has had the boldneſs to Addreſs his Libel to You the moſt Noble Lords and Worthy Patriots of the two Houſes of Parliament; I like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at laſt take the Confidence to throw this Anſwer of mine at your Feet, with my humble Petition in the behalf of almoſt a whole Diſtracted Nation: That in your great Wiſdom you will take ſuch moderate courſes as may once more make us a happy people, that you would ſecure us againſt <hi>Popery</hi> without deſtroying <hi>Monarchy,</hi> or which is the ſame thing, making this an Elective Kingdom, which has ever been Hereditary; that you would take care of that Church which is ſo miſerably beſet with enemies on both ſides, and which is ſo firm a friend to the State, that they have ever both riſen and fallen together. Laſtly I muſt conjure you by the Spirits of all thoſe <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men, that in our laſt unnatural Wars fell on both ſides, by the Heroes of <hi>Edgehill, of Naſeby, of Worceſter,</hi> and of all thoſe Fatal Fields that were then Fought; by the Cries of the Widows which then were made, and the Curſes of thoſe Mothers which that Cruel Scene made to be ſo no more; by all the Miſeries we remember, and all that we can fear or expect: And laſtly by the bloud of that Royal Martyr, whoſe memory we to this day celebrate, I conjure you as you expect to anſwer it to God and a whole Nation, to take care above all things that we have not a Civil War entailed upon us, to ſweep away what the former has left: that we may never more run into that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tremity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Madneſs, which not long ſince made one of the moſt Powerful and Happy Kingdoms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>ld, the pity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of all the Nations round about her.</p>
            <p>And having made this moſt humble Addreſs to your Honourab. Aſſembly, I ſhall take my leave of my Reader, in an Ode of <hi>Horace</hi> to this purpoſe, a very little aſcer'd; 'Tis his 7th. Epod to the People of <hi>Rome,</hi> his Countrey-men, dehorting 'em from engaging in a <hi>Civil War</hi> twice in one Age, whereby the eaſineſs of the application of it to our preſent times and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we may find that the people of <hi>England</hi> have learnt ſomewhat elſe from <hi>Rome</hi> beſides its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which is at leaſt even as deſtructive as that.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="translation">
               <head>Ad Populum <hi>Anglicanum</hi> deteſtatio Belli Civilis. <hi>Hor.</hi> Ep. 7.</head>
               <l>QUo, quo ſceleſti ruitis? aut cur dexteris</l>
               <l>Aptantur enſes conditi?</l>
               <l>Parumne campis atque Neptuno ſuper</l>
               <l>Fuſum eſt <hi>Britanni</hi> Sanguinis?</l>
               <l>Non factuoſas invidae Lutetiae</l>
               <l>Ut <hi>Anglus</hi> arces ureret,</l>
               <l>Iterumve Rex ut Gallicus deſcenderet</l>
               <l>Noſtris Catenatus viis,</l>
               <l>Sed ut, ſecundum vota Gallorum ſua</l>
               <l>Gens haec periret dextera.</l>
               <l>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hic lupis mos nec fuit leonibus</l>
               <l>Unquam, niſi in diſpar, feris.</l>
               <l>Furorne caecus, an rapit vis acrior?</l>
               <l>An culpa? Reſponſum date.</l>
               <l>Tacent &amp; oro pallor albus inficit</l>
               <l>Monteſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> perculſae ſtupent.</l>
               <l>Sic eſt: Acerba fata <hi>Brittones</hi> agunt,</l>
               <l>Sceluſque Regiae necis.</l>
               <l>Ut immerentis pegma tinxit <hi>Caroli</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sacer nepotibus cruor.</l>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="translation">
               <pb facs="tcp:137224:9"/>
               <head>To the People of <hi>England;</hi> A Deteſtation of <hi>Civil War, out of</hi> Horace<hi>'s 7. Ep.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>OH! Whither do ye ruſh, and thus prepare?</l>
               <l>To rouze again the ſleeping War?</l>
               <l>Has then ſo little <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Bloud been ſpilt</l>
               <l>On Sea, and Land with equal guilt?</l>
               <l>Not that again; we might our Arms advance,</l>
               <l>To check the inſolent Pride of <hi>France.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not that once more we might in Fetters bring</l>
               <l>An humble Captive <hi>Gallic</hi> King:</l>
               <l>But to the wiſh of the inſulting <hi>Gaul,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That we by our own hands ſhould fall</l>
               <l>Nor Wolves nor Lyons bear ſo fierce a mind;</l>
               <l>They hurt not their own Savage kind.</l>
               <l>Is it blind Rage, or Zeal, more blind &amp; ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Or Guilt, yet ſtronger, drives you on?</l>
               <l>Anſwer; but none can anſwer; mute and pale</l>
               <l>They ſtand; Guilt does o're Words prevail.</l>
               <l>'Tis ſo: Heavens Juſtice threatens us from high;</l>
               <l>And a King's Death from Earth does cry;</l>
               <l>E'r ſince the Martyrs Innocent blood was ſhed,</l>
               <l>Upon our Fathers, and on Ours, and on our</l>
               <l>Children head.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
